好
大家听得到我在说什么吗
学生：听得清
非常好
从哪里开始呢
像上周课的开头我问你们关于util实验那样开始吧
这回
我想先问问你们关于syscall实验的事
因为在上周四这个实验就已经截止了
所以
有人愿意来分享分享吗
比如你在实验中发现的有趣的事
或者是讨厌的bug
又或者是你犯下的某个愚蠢的错误
你可以分享任何有关于syscall实验的想法
只要愿意分享
那就是非常好的 (之后一部分为学生分享，比较难懂，可以跳过)
（学生）不知道咋的
（学生）我删除了fork中那个必须备份掩码的部分（copy over the mask 存疑？）
（学生）然后我让它运行了
（学生）然后我又改变了些别的地方
（学生）然后我测试了一下
我想你的音频可能断开了
（学生）非常抱歉
（学生）你能听到我说话吗
我现在听到了  （学生）好的
（学生）嗯好的
（学生）不知道为啥
（学生）我删除了掩码的备份（the copy of the mask存疑）
（学生）然后我的fork就不起作用了
（学生）我就在想为啥它不起作用了
（学生）我花费了很长时间
（学生）才弄明白我错在哪儿
（学生）我意识到
（学生）我只是不小心删除了那行代码
有没有人听不到luca的声音？
或者只是我这里的问题？
（学生）我觉得是你那里的问题，我可以听到他说话
好的
看来是我这里的问题
抱歉，现在应该好了
（学生）现在你能听到我说话吗 （老师）可以 （学生）好的
（学生）我还担心是我这里的问题
不
完全是我的问题
非常好，
有没有其他人愿意分享？
关于syscall实验的都行
实验中任何有趣的事情都可以分享
这个实验
是不是太可怕了
你们是不是想把它从课程中去掉，再也不碰了
（学生）我想要发言（此处翻译时译者十分迷惑）
（学生）显然
（学生）这些一般性的语句是顺序关联的
（学生）额
（学生）在对函数进行跟踪(trace)之前
（学生）我对系统调用函数
（学生）进行了大量的推演计算
（学生）来确定是否真的需要进行跟踪(tracing)
（学生）所有的系统调用都被正确地追踪到了
（学生）除了trace调用
（学生）我当时真的感到很困扰
（学生）直到，大概是David吧
（学生）他指出我应该
（学生）在对函数进行跟踪(trace)之后
（学生）再开始推演计算,就是这样
我很高兴你可以
察觉到这一点
嗯，顺序确实很重要
尤其对于页表来说
我认为
顺序同样重要
在我们整个课程中也是
注意事物的顺序
这很重要
在页表中
最好不要重写其内容
（学生）我也有一些问题
（学生）关于这些问题
（学生）我仍然感到困惑
（学生）我的内核代码中
（学生）有一大堆debugging打印语句
（学生）我运行了trace
（学生）并设置了掩码的所有位
（学生）大体上跟踪了所有系统调用
（学生）我想我应该是看到了一大堆
（学生）对print语句的追踪
（学生）出现在了内核中
（学生）嗯然后。。。
（学生）我猜想我的打印。。。
（学生）我的打印程序尝试
（学生）输出到控制台
（学生）但是。。。额，输出到控制台，但是
（学生）我很好奇为什么。。。额
（学生）我猜我只是疑惑于
（学生）为什么我们可以在内核里使用printf
嗯好的，我还没有。。。额
我最近还没有看printf代码
但我想应该有一个文件
printf.c，如果你想看的话，你应该可以看到这个文件
以及，如果你想要。。。
理解内核里发生了什么
那我想
printf函数应该被实现在那个文件里
至少我们的版本应该是这样
我不是太清楚，也许。。。
也许有其他老师
可以告诉你具体情况
（老师2）内核中这些print
（老师2）不应该出现在你的追踪(traces)中
（老师2）因为内核中的printf
（老师2）不会调用任何系统调用
（学生）是的，那就是我所想的
（学生）或许。。。或许，输出的追踪信息
（学生）并非来自于那些语句
（老师2）是的，我不认为它们来自
（老师2）内核中的打印语句
（学生）好的
好的，如果
没有其他人想关于syscall实验做发言的话
我想我们可以
开始今天的课程了
我们将会谈一谈
将C转换到汇编的过程
以及处理器（processors），以及。。。
今天的课更像是一堂实践课程
至少，我们的目的在于
让你们熟悉一下risc-v
熟悉一下处理器
熟悉一下汇编语言
以及，熟悉一下
risc-v中的调用约定
这些对于页表是非常重要的
不，不是特别重要
不过，当然了
在这周即将布置的traps实验中
这些将有助于调试
以及实现功能
因为
你们接下来要做的事和陷阱框架（trap frames，译者认为可译作系统调用框架）
以及栈，以及其他种种类似的东西密切相关
所以，那就是
今天的目标
我讲课的第一个目标是。。。嗯，这里可能
有一些内容
是对6.004的复习
也有可能包含
其他的你已经学过的基础课程
我只想简单地回顾一下
比如
看一看如何把C语言转换到
汇编
以及可能有一些关于处理器的知识and maybe a little bit about processor
然后
这里提一句
上课时如果你有感到疑惑的地方
你可以随时打断我
嗯，你们知道的，在C当中
我们有一个main函数
main函数会做一些工作
它可能会打印些什么
然后退出
这看起来很不错
但是，你们都在6.004中学过的
处理器
其实并不能理解C语言
它们只能理解
汇编语言
或者更确切地说
它们只能理解
汇编语言的二进制码
在这张图片上
我在主板中
圈出了risc-v处理器
当我们说某个处理器是risc-v时
这意味着
它可以理解risc-v指令集
所以每一个处理器都有一个关联的isa（指令集架构）
或者关联的指令
该指令集对于该处理器来说
是有效的（可执行的）
每一个指令
都有一个关联的二进制码或操作码
当处理器运行时
遇上特定格式的二进制码
它就会知道执行什么操作
你知道的
这个主板上的处理器
正好能够理解
由C语言编译出的risc-v汇编
所以
让C代码在你的处理器上运行的大致步骤是
写一段C代码
把它编译成汇编
在这步骤之中
会有一些链接（linking）操作以及其他类似操作
但是我们现在上的不是编译原理课（就不多说了）
然后
汇编将被翻译成二进制码
这就是
目标文件
或者说是你看到的.o文件
如果你曾注意到
你的实验文件夹里有什么
在你运行“make qemu”命令后
你将会看到一连串的.o文件
这些就是目标文件
处理器可以理解它们
还有你们已经看到的asm文件
嗯你们好像还没开始写
但是，你们可以回想一下
有一个usas.pl文件被编译成了一个usys.s文件
那个.s文件里面
就是汇编语言
所以你们已经看到过risc-v汇编代码了
如果你上过6.004课程
我相信你们已经看过
大量的汇编代码
总得来说
汇编的结构化程度看起来不如C语言
所以你们只能一行一行的阅读
那些指令
你们会看到一些简单的玩意
比如add
抑或是malt等等
诸如此类的非常多
在汇编中
没有直观的控制流
没有直观的循环语句
没有像C语言中一样直观的函数
你知道的，我们只能看到标签（labels）
而不是真实的函数定义
汇编是相当低级的语言（计算机科学层面）
有大量的其他语言
可以被编译成
汇编语言
嗯，这些步骤
对诸如C++之类的语言
同样适用
你知道的
任何编译型语言
最终在底层都会变成汇编的形式
嗯嗯，这就是
让我们的计算机
能够理解我们写的C代码
的基本步骤
不过，你可能注意到了
在课程中
我们一直都有提到risc-v汇编
以及risc-v处理器
那是因为
额，这件事非常重要
因为汇编语言的种类有很多
所以对于你们个人来说
你们是不太可能用到risc-v的
你们不太可能会在risc-v处理器上
运行linux
事实上绝大多数现代计算机
都运行在
x86处理器上
有时候你们会看到x86-64
这是一个不同（于risc-v）的指令集架构
这是一个不同的指令集
它看起来和risc-v十分相似
但这才是你们自己的个人电脑上
常常见到的指令集
如果你们用intel的话
intel的cpu实现了x86指令集
amd的cpu也实现了（x86指令集）
这两者（指x86与risc-v）之间
有着相当重要的区别
乍一看很相似
实际上它们并没有那么相似
归根结底
risc-v被我们称作risc
risc意为
精简指令集
x86-64则被称为cisc
或者说是复杂指令集
在它们之间
有一系列的不同点
其中一点就是
x86-64中指令的数量（与risc-v对比）
事实上
这一点可以大书特书
而在intel的手册中
我们可以找到
risc要实现多少条指令
（x86-64的）参考手册（这句发言逻辑略混乱）
是三本厚书
那里面包含了整个（x86-64）指令集
有统计资料表明
自x86-64于70年代发布以来
intel一直以
每月3条指令的速度
向x86-64指令集中添加指令
我估计
x86-64指令集大概有
15000条指令
而另一方面
就risc-v来讲
仅仅两份文档
就涵盖了risc-v指令的所有内容
我们并不打算
让你们
死记硬背课程中的
每一条risc-v指令
但如果你对这些指令感兴趣的话
或者对某个指令感到迷惑
。。。
你可以到课程网站上
在references标签下可以看到
在risc-v段落下我们放了一个链接
有已获得授权的指令
也有未获得授权的指令
这个文档
可以给你提供一系列关于指令集架构的
信息
不过请注意这个是240页
。。。
这个是135页
比起x86-64指令集（的手册）
这两份文档明显小很多
risc-v的这个特点
对我们来说非常棒
在risc-v中，有（比x86）更少的指令
。。。
这些指令也更简单
我之所以这么说是因为
x86-64中的指令实在太多了
我提到的指令就是
像malt或者sub那样的东西
x86-64中大量的指令集完成不止一件任务
。。。
它们执行了一系列
复杂的操作
并给出结果
而在risc-v中就不是这样
risc-v往往
。。。
执行更少的操作
所以它每次的运行周期更短
x86-64和risc-v的差别
只是设计师所做出的一种权衡
。。。
事实上并没有。。。
嗯你知道的。。。
并没有真正意义上的
精简指令集
比复杂指令集更好的说法
。。。
两种指令集都有它们各自的用途
以此类推
risc-v还有一个很酷的优点
与x86不同的是
risc-v是开源的
它是市面上仅有的开源指令集之一
所以这意味着
任何人都能用risc-v开发处理器
。。。
risc诞生于
uc berkeley的一个项目
所以uc berkeley是其发源地
从那时起
就有许多公司使用并赞助risc-v
你可以在网上找到名单
但是你知道的
有大量的公司
致力于赞助开源指令集
我记得最近
（某公司）
（大概是risc-v处理器的主板制造商）
发布了一则公告
宣称
他们将发布
用于个人PC的主板
你们懂得
那是一个为个人PC设计的
risc-v处理器
我记得
这个消息是上周发布的
也可能是两周前
如果你对这玩意感到好奇
嗯应该会很好奇
上完6.s081之后我就很想用一用risc-v
。。。
到时候
就有一个能让我们在自己的电脑上
运行linux的（risc-v）处理器了
在你们的日常生活中
最可能使用到的就是精简指令集
也许你们并没有注意到
比如arm汇编
arm也是一个精简指令集
。。。
高通的骁龙系列处理器
就是arm架构的
处理器
所以如果你有一个安卓手机
你很有可能
在使用精简指令集
即使你用的是iOS
iOS。。。我忘了那个（处理器的）名字。。。
苹果公司
也在它们的处理器中
使用了某些版本的
arm架构
iPad，iPhone
以及大多数苹果设备都运行在那个处理器上
精简指令集
可谓到处都是
如果你想在现实中
而非qemu中找到risc-v去使用
你可以在诸如一体机（intergrated devices）上
找到它
它并不像x86-64那样
随处可见
但是。。嗯。。。
我想，正如刚刚lucas在聊天中说的
我想苹果正在将macs（指mac系列PC？）
迁移到arm架构
我记得应该就是这两年的事情
可以肯定地说
他们正朝着精简指令集发展
考虑到intel指令集架构
如此庞大
以及考虑到其根源
全在于
他们非常关心
向后兼容性
因此即使是三四十年前的
intel代码
也可以
。。。
在现代intel处理器上运行
intel并没有删除任何指令
所以他们（的cpu）可以保持
向后兼容性
而risc-v则更为现代化
所以不用担心（risc-v会存在这些历史遗留问题）
让我们回到这些手册
risc-v（手册）很独特地分开了
这是risc-v中的
基整数指令集(base integer instruction)
额（开始混乱）
（混乱地吐槽intel中？）
如果处理器有15000条指令
我们几乎不可能有效地
在流水线上传送指令（pipeline them）
我们为啥需要这么多
我的意思是
这么多指令只是为了向后兼容性
是否使用完全取决于你自己
是否觉得（向后兼容性）重要
不过我估计这些指令中
绝大多数
都是cmd使用的
专属的
一类特殊指令
你不可能（会用上这些指令）
我从来没见过谁
能完全利用15000条intel指令
这些指令中绝大多数的诞生
都是为了满足向后兼容性的需求
以及cmd的需求
正如我之前说的（回到正题 ）
这个
基整数指令集
包含了所有正常的像add
multiply
之类的指令
然后处理器可以选择性地实现一些其他模块
你可以在这边看到（这些模块）
可能在你的屏幕上显示的并不清晰
比如
如果你想要一个
支持单精度浮点数的标准扩展的
处理器
你可以导入f模块
risc-v更容易
支持
向后兼容性
因为你知道你导入并支持了
哪些模块
然后编译器可以做出选择
编译器会说：好的
这个处理器告诉我
它支持这些模块
所以我只可以用这些模块来编译这些代码
好的，（某学生）说看起来
用x86处理器
代替risc-v处理器的唯一优势
就是你可以获得性能提升
然而这些性能提升
带来了大量的代价与复杂性
以及潜在安全问题
我的问题是为什么我们仍然在用x86
而非迁移到其他处理器架构
比如risc-v
嗯好的，主要原因是
整个世界一直在使用x86
（大概有多少年）我太记得清了
。。。
risc-v也是非常现代化的
整个世界一直都在用x86
如果突然地
开始把处理器都换成risc-v
这会带来很大的风险
这会使得很多重要的东西
失去支持
also there are like intel does do
interesting things within their
processors
it's like security wise there are
enclaves and intel processors and
there's things that um
they've been doing in recent years to
try to try and give you extra
added security and uh some of those
instructions that intel does implement
which are hyper-specific
can be really efficient for certain
computations uh and so they have so many
instructions that there's often you know
a perfect instruction for a situation
that may be more efficient than
than what exists within risk five but a
more practical answer is that risk five
is relatively new and we just don't
you know nobody's really making
processors for personal computers i
think the
sci 5 announcement is super recent um
and
they're kind of the first people to be
doing that so on a practical level
that and the inability to run all the
software design for intel
is is my best answer
so we've been now chatting a little bit
about assembly so i just wanted to
take a look at some actual assembly code
so here is uh the
c code for what's below so this is a
simple function that has an accumulator
we loop from zero to n and we
sum up all the numbers from uh from zero
to n
and then return that value and uh
at its simplest level you know this is
the easiest kind of assembly that you
can get out of compiling that program
if you actually go into your own
computer and you write the c
code and you try to compile it you will
end up with something
that likely looks quite different and
that's true for a variety of reasons we
haven't
some of which we'll get to and some of
which are compiler specific
so modern compilers make a large number
of optimizations
um within when they compile your c2
assembly and so your assembly
instructions may look different
for instance while you're debugging in
gdv you may come across something that
tells you that it's
some variable has been optimized out and
that means that the compiler decided it
didn't need that variable
uh and so that'll be gone effectively
from the program
but yeah and it's at its most
straightforward
we're moving uh the value that's in a
zero to t
zero we're setting a zero to zero and
then
we are just adding what's in t zero to a
zero
for every iteration of a loop until t
zero reaches zero
and that's all that's going on in this
piece uh amir your hands erased
yeah i was wondering what dot section
dot text
and dot global do global means that you
can
include this from other files so if we
actually hop into
uh let's see def.h
this is the file that you're uh will if
you aren't already you will become quite
familiar with this
includes basically all of the functions
within the kernel that you may want to
be using
and uh within here you know we can see
that in my
my file i've included the definitions to
these functions
and so that dot global make sure that
that these these functions can be called
from other places
and dot text just says this is code
so if you recall from figure 3.4
in the book so that's if we go
to the book
and we go into page tables
process address space so in here in this
diagram
that's the same thing this is text so it
just means code
that answer your question okay thanks
and so if we want to run let's say we
have some assembly
also if you ever find yourself
interested in
what the kernel looks like we can go
inside the after you compile you can
look in the file kernel
kernel.asm and this is the full kind of
assembly for the kernel
of xv6 and each of these numbers on the
left here
is a label that tells you where in
memory this
in this instruction will be and that'll
come in quite handy
and so here is the here's the actual uh
here's the actual assembly code and you
can see the labels for the functions
and where they're declared so this is
this is a can be really really useful as
we're debugging code
and hopefully i'll be able to show that
in a second
but for now we'll jump back to this
first function
sum2 and we'll just see how we can
examine that
inside of gdd so the first step is i
have my two windows here
what's the difference between asm and s
files
um i'm not 100
certain they're both assembly i think
the dot asm file includes a bunch of
extra annotations that aren't included
in dot
s so usually when you compile your c
code to
dot s you'll end up with something that
doesn't include all of those line
numbers and things like that so
if you're curious about how we get the
dot asm file i think the makefile
um will tell you the exact steps used to
get that and so
if we're we're in our terminal we have
our two uh two windows
so the first thing to do is of course uh
get qmu up and running so we can
start it within gdb mode so now we're
we're frozen here
and then we can start gdb uh
and what uh what what what uh professor
crasher showed last week
and which i think some people were
excited about if you type tui
enable you get this nice window which is
empty for now but will come in
quite useful as you're debugging so we
can set a breakpoint and i should note
that all this code is living inside the
kernel none of this is in user space
so we don't have any of those annoying
problems setting breakpoints so i can
set a breakpoint
in the function sum2 and then just
continue running
and run that function and now
so the first window that you see in tui
is the source window
uh yes as david is saying those those
numbers on the left of kernel.asm
are really useful when you're debugging
things and you get an address
it'll tell you so you can see now even
here we can see that the program so pc
here in gdb
is the program counter so we can see
this address 8 0 0
so on and so forth if we go into
kernel.asm
and we search for that specific address
we can see that it's the
uh well it comes up twice because it's a
function call but if we look here this
is that address
it's the top of the sum2 function so
if you see any time you see one of these
um
all the kernel addresses will look
something like 0x8000
some numbers those uh those addresses
you can jump straight into kernel.asm
and find the exact
line of assembly where the problem is
occurring and then you can set your
breakpoints accordingly
but for now uh that top window in tui
is source and if we want to look at
specifically the assembly we can do
layout ngdasm
and that'll give us all of the assembly
instructions
and we can also look at the registers if
we type layout reg we'll get assembly
and registers and if you find yourself
you know wanting to scroll through
things
now that we have three windows we need
to specify which one is focused so if i
want to look through all the registers
i'm going to focus
reg and now my focus is on the register
window so if i
move the arrow keys or scroll it'll
start scrolling that window
so for now we can focus on the assembly
window
and once we're here we can see all of
the things uh
so let's see we can see in the registry
register window we can see that t
0 contains this value we can see that a0
contains this value
and as we step through the assembly we
can watch
see okay t 0 just got the value of a0
which was
5 and it's nicely highlighted the
register that's changed
here and we can just keep remember if we
if we push enter we get the
most recently executed instructions so
we can go through
all right we set a0 to 0 and now we can
just kind of watch ourselves go through
this loop
and sum up the values
and again this is like a complete you
know toy function
and then we can continue and you know
live our lives and if you're ever
curious about
what kind of breakpoints you've set or
you lose track of what you were doing
if you type info break or break points
you can see all of the breakpoints that
you've set in your code
and you can even see okay this
breakpoint has already been hit one time
and you get lots of useful information
doing that
if you don't want to have the register
window but you do want to look at the
registers
info reg or info registers or ireg or
any of the
numerous gdb shortenings
will bring up the register window as
well
um so with that is there any are there
any questions about
gdd um simple ones i know it's been
um there's been lots of post sump shots
about it so
now is a good time to just ask uh some
straightforward we'll i'll be showing
more
usage of ddb what command did you use to
open the multiple windows so i use tmux
so i can show just from scratch uh if we
go
here and i open a new terminal so here's
just a blank terminal
if you type tmux and this is available
on athena
i'll address the next question in a
second so now i'm in tmux which you can
tell by this
green bar at the bottom and if you want
to
get so there's a couple ways you can do
multiple windows in tebow tmux
uh if you're so you can type control bc
and uh i know that's sometimes if you're
used to using emacs that will make a lot
of sense but
um normal people who don't use emacs
that's hitting control and then d and
then hitting
c on its own afterwards that will get
you a second window which you can then
navigate between with control b
and then p control b and then n to go
previous and next
yeah and david just posted a t-much
cheat sheet which is useful
and if you want to split the windows i
think it's ctrl b and then
the percent sign will split them um
vertically and then sing a double
control b
and then double quote we'll split them
uh horizontally
and so that's how we get them and if
we're in this state we can use control b
and o to jump between our windows
so that's what's that's how i got the
multiple windows yeah i don't care
um and then ahmed asked
why is this displaying assembly
addresses again instead of c line
numbers
ah so because the the function
so if we go back to the assembly
function
this is implemented entirely in assembly
and not at all in c
and so there just aren't any associated
c line numbers for this
um if we were to
set a breakpoint so if you type delete
you'll delete all your breakpoints uh so
i cleared the old one if i now set a
breakpoint in
demo one so that's a c breakpoint and
continue
and run this now if i go here and type
layout split
i'll get the c and the assembly um or if
i just want the c
source i can do layout source and i'll
just get the c
so that's uh that's what's going on it's
just a quirk of the fact that this
doesn't have associated c code and so we
don't see seedline numbers
any other any other questions about gdb
tmox and that that sort of thing
so layout split is the one that you use
to bring up this extra window of the
source and assembly and so on right
yes yes so layout uh if you do layout
split that'll get you
source and assembly layout source will
get you just source
asm we'll get you just assembly and the
registers are their own thing where if
you type layout reg
i think yeah that'll bring up the
registers but
unfortunately i don't know of a way to
get
the register of the assembly and the c
code all at the same time outside of
using inforeg with layout split
i have a question um so when we set the
break point uh add a line right it
displays the address of the like in this
case break point to add
0x 354. um
what any instruction might have multiple
uh
any like line of code in c might have
multiple instructions
so which one does its uh show i believe
it shows the first one
and uh it's to you for the person who
asked to
start the tui it's i think it's tui
enable not enable to ui sorry i think
um yeah again there's like a hundred
cheat sheets out here for gdb
and for tmux as well so if you ever find
yourself lost
i t gdp even has its own inbuilt um
its own thing called apropos so if you
look for apropos
tui it will actually show you all of the
commands that involve tui
so yeah uh this can be quite useful but
it can also be a little bit overwhelming
um if you do apropos dash b it'll give
you even more information i think
um i don't remember i i don't use it
often myself but if you if you do
find or if you forget the exact way to
type the command in in gdb and you don't
feel like googling it apropos
will will uh often be able to find
exactly what you're looking for in
addition to a whole bunch of stuff you
weren't looking for
um yeah so
that can be quite useful gdp is
extremely well documented as well
so um yeah if you ever find yourself
lost
you know google is your friend um
so now that we we've kind of been over
assembly and
and risk five and these sort of things i
want to dive a little bit more into the
specifics
um of what you you really need to know
for the
lab coming up and also is this will be a
little bit of review from the document
that you've all
of course as diligent students read
through thoroughly
uh in preparation for this lecture
um so you know this table will of course
be uh wildly familiar to you all
and uh from from both double o4
and from what you've read and this is
the table of registers and
registers are little you know locations
on the cpu or on the processor
pre-defined that it can use to store
values
and this is important because assembly
operations
if we remember from the assembly code
the assembly doesn't operate on memory
it operates on registers so when we do
add when we do subtract
we're operating on registers um
and so what you'll often see as the
pattern for
for writing assembly is we'll have some
kind of a load
so we'll load some value
to a register and that value can be from
memory
or it can be from another uh register
and and here i'm referring to load in
general not the load instruction
um and then we'll operate
so we'll perform some operation on the
register
and then if we care about the result of
that operation outside of the return
address
we will um will store that
register to somewhere
to some locate that will store that
register to some location
do that in memory or to another register
and so that's that's uh generally the
way things work and and registers are
the absolute fastest way to perform
any sort of calculation uh or to access
any value and that's why
um it's important to use them and also
why
we prefer using registers over using
memory so if you remember from
the reading when we call functions so
you can see here that registers
a0 to 7 and
in general when we speak about registers
we
we will be referring to them by their
abi name um
not only is it less confusing it's just
a standard and it's also the way that
you'll write assembly code
um this you know these actual numbers
are not super important
the only case where it does matter is
for the compressed version of risk 5
instructions
and if you want to know more about that
feel free to read up about it the basic
idea is that risk
5 normal instructions are 64 bits
but there's also a compressed version in
which instructions are 16 bits
and we use less registers and the
registers we use in that case
are 8 through 15. those are the
registers that are available to us
so i think somebody had a question about
you know why is this s1 register
x9 why is it separated from all of the
other s
registers and my guess is that that's
why
that we separated from all of the other
ones because it's available
in compressed instruction mode whereas
s2 to 11 or not
and so that's the idea so that's that's
for compressed but outside of that
registers will always be referred to by
their
abi name and so a0 to a7 are used for
function arguments
but if we have a function that takes
more than the eight arguments that those
registers give us access to
we do need to use memory but that's this
is kind of an illustration of the fact
that we don't want to use memory when we
can use registers
we only we only use a memory if we have
to
and this uh this column here the saver
column
this is also extremely important when
we're discussing registers caller versus
callee saved
and um the terms are
i confuse them regularly caller and
callie they only differ by one letter
the easiest way that i found to remember
them is that
caller saved registers are not
preserved
across a function call
so and callee saved registers
are preserved what i mean by this
is that
a caller saved register can be
overwritten
by the function so let's say i have
function a
which calls function b any registers
being used by function a
that are caller saved call function b
can overwrite when it gets called and i
think a good illustration of this
is the return address because you know
you can see that the return address is
caller saved
and that's important because every
function needs to use the return address
so when a calls b it's important that b
be able to
overwrite the value in the return
address hence why it's caller saved
and callee saved registers are just our
convention that we use
the frame pointer is important for that
reason
and those are preserved across the
function calls so basically any register
that is caller saved
the function that is making the call
needs to worry about those registers
and if they're calling saved the
function that is being called
needs to worry about preserving the
value in those registers
and again you know i i regularly confuse
the two
and find myself returning to this table
to remind myself about what they do
and so you know you if you remember from
the reading
all of these registers are 64 bits wide
so they have 64
places where we can put things and
the various data types are made to fit
into those 64 bits
based on the calling convention so if we
have a 32-bit integer
depending on how it's whether or not
it's sign extended you know we'll either
add zeros or ones to the front of that
integer
in order to make it 64 bits to put in
these registers
so before we move on uh does anybody
have questions about
registers or things things of that
nature
i have a question can you have a
can you put a return value in a1
yes it's a good question so um i think
in theory
you can the reason why we say a0 to a1
is if a function returns a long long
which is 128 bits
so if you remember from the reading if a
function argument is 100 is more than
a pointer word and so when we refer to
the prior word size we're saying 64 bits
so if we have something that is twice
the size of a pointer word
um we can put that in a register pair
and so the same convention holds true
for return addresses where if we have
something that's
the size of twice a pointer word we can
stick that in a0 and
a1 and use that as the return address i
think you'll run into problems if you
only try to put something in a1
make sense thanks
why are the registers not like
continuous
so why is like a zero and one separate
from sorry no that's a that's a bad
example what's why is s1
separate from s2 why are the a's in
between like is there any point in that
yeah so uh i mentioned this briefly
earlier but there is a
compressed this is a guess i don't i
don't know for sure
but there's a compressed version of the
risc 5
instructions which are 16 bits in size
as opposed to 64.
and you would use that to try and
make your code take less space in memory
and when you use those 16-bit
instructions you only have
accesses to registers 8 through 15.
so i think s1 is separate from s2 to 11
because they want to make it clear that
s1 is available to you
in the compressed instruction mode
whereas s2 to 11 aren't
um and the reason you know i don't know
why they picked x
x eight to 15 but i suspect that that's
just they looked at a bunch of code and
we're like oh these are the most
commonly used registers
[Music]
any other questions
i had a question um besides the frame
pointer the stack pointer and all
uh i i don't know why we would need more
call
callista registers but we do have
like a bunch of them yeah the s1s
to 11s those are just for i believe used
there for freedom for the compiler
or for the programmer to use um so there
are maybe there are certain cases where
you want
you want to guarantee that something is
still around
after after your function call the
compiler can choose to use
s1 211 to do that
i don't have like on hand a specific
example of where that's useful
but i'm sure it shows up where
having a callee save value is important
but these are basically basically you
know programmer or compiler's choice to
use
that's 1 to 11.
and i should note that these these
floating point registers they're for
floating point arithmetic
i as far as i'm aware you won't see them
in this class
and so you don't really need to worry
about them
okay so we started talking a little bit
about function calls
and so with that i want to
move us into discussion of the stack
so this is this is
we're talking about the stack and
the stack if you've seen it likely
before
the reason why the stack is important is
it
it's what keeps our functions
organized and sane and it's what allows
and what makes functions work it what
it's what makes return
work and it's also uh where often we'll
find ourselves
saving our registers and things like
that
um
so here i've
given just a pretty simple um
[Music]
layout of what a stack looks like and so
each of these
boxes here is what we refer to
as a stack frame
and every time we get
which are generated by function calls
um every time we call a function
that function makes for itself its own
stack frame
and which is in which it uses itself and
does that by moving around the stack
pointer
so here's the stack pointer and this is
uh
and it's very important to remember with
stacks
we start from high addresses
and we grow downwards to
low addresses so the stack grows down
always
and so you'll see that the arithmetic
for a stack pointer is uh
is usually done via subtraction when we
want to make a new stack frame
in assembly so the stack grows downwards
and stack frames for a function contain
saved registers local variables
um also like i like i was saying if you
run out
of argument registers additional
arguments will show up on the stack
and so not at stack frames are not all
the same size
even though they are in this diagram
that's not the case different functions
have different numbers of local
variables different safe registers
so on and so forth and so stack frames
will be different sizes but the two
things that you can definitely count on
which are important is that uh the
return address will always be
on the first thing and the frame pointer
the previous frames frame pointer is
also going to show up on the stack
at a predictable location so
the two important registers here are sp
which you know as we discussed
is used for this is the bottom of the
stack
or generally you know it's the location
of the stack
and then fp is our also important
register and this points to the top of
the current
frame and this is important because
that means that the return address and
the previous fp
will always be at a fixed location
from the current frame pointer so that
means that
if i want to find my return address or i
want to find the previous frame
i can always get to those values by
looking at the current frame pointer
and the reason why we store the previous
frame pointer is to allow us
to jump back so once this function
returns we can move this into fp
and all of a sudden fp again will go
from pointing to this
this stack frame to now pointing to this
stack frame
and so we use the frame pointer to
manipulate our stack frames
and make sure we're always pointing to
the one corresponding
to the correct function
and that's that's kind of how things uh
how things are done
and uh the these pieces of the stack
um need to be created by assembly
and so everything's everything in that
calling conventions
document that you read about that's all
um enforced by
effectively by the compiler so the
compiler adheres to
the calling convention and it's what
generates the stack frame
it generates the assembly code that
makes our stack frames look
correct so often at the top of a
function you'll see what's called
a function prolog
and then there will be the body of the
function
and then there will be an epilogue
that shows up after that so this is kind
of like
what an assembly uh
function will often look like and we'll
take a look at that
now so here i have another function
something so you you'll you'll note that
studently that sum2 did not have
any of these things that it it should if
it was a proper function
and this works fine because it's simple
enough so it does all of its
computations on
a0 and so things are things are good and
we're also not it's a it's a leaf
function
so you'll see if you see the term leaf
function that's a function that doesn't
call another function
and the functions are special in that
they don't need to
worry about saving their own return
address
or saving really any of the caller saved
registers
because they're going to they're not
going to make another function call so
they don't have to be
as careful some then double on the other
hand
is not a leaf function so you can see
here it calls
um sum2 and so it does need to include
that
that prolog and so we see here that we
are subtracting
16 from the stack pointer so we're
making space
on our stack we're storing the return
address
for something double on the stack and
then we make our call to sum2
and after that all this this function
does is it calls sum2 and then
doubles the result doubles the result
turned by some two and here you can see
the
epilog so we load the return address
back in to ra and
delete our stack frame and then jump out
of the function
and so we can run that to make sure it
does what we would expect
we can go here
we can run so if we run demo2 or demo
one we got a result of 15
for the sum and i'll tell you that demo
two just uh just calls something double
and indeed
you know it happily doubles the sum
returned by some two and
so a question i have for for anybody
what happens if we uh delete
this prologue and f so what happens
if we just have this as our function
something double can anybody predict
what's going to happen
i mean one thing is that some then
double wouldn't know
the return address that it should return
to so upon calling
sum to that's going to override the
return address to be
some then double so at the end of thumb
then double
it's not going to return to its original
call
yeah exactly um and we can see that
that's what happens
again so if we
exit out of this and we exit out of this
and we recompile with now with our
broken function
we can take a look at exactly what's
going to happen so we can actually
set our breakpoint for something double
and set up tui and let it continue so if
we now run demo 2
okay we're at some then double and
again this is an assembly only function
so we're going to want to look at it in
assembly so we'll do layout asm layout
reg because it's important what's in the
registers in this case
and you'll see that gdb knows a whole
bunch of extra information
and so we can see that
we can see that ra currently so the
return address currently points to demo2
the plus 18 so
it points effectively into the function
demo2
and now we can run um we can just kind
of step through our function and see
what happens so we've called sum2
and immediately we can see that the
return address was
overwritten by sum 2 to now point to sum
then double plus 4
which makes sense you know that's what
we'd expect if we go back into our code
we call sum 2
and so sum2 should return to uh to here
and now we can step through
[Music]
you know so on up and uh
then we get back into
whoops the wrong s
okay so now we're here and now when sum
then double returns
as exactly as amir pointed out um its
return it has not restored its own
return address
and instead its return address is still
the one that was used by
um sum two and so we will
get into an infinite loop where we just
keep doing this over and over and over
again and we'll never terminate from it
and so this is a i think this is a good
illustration of why it's important to
keep track of our caller versus callee
saved registers
and hopefully this also shows that you
can use kind of gdb to
debug these sorts of these sorts of
problems so let's
restore what we had and we'll go
into some other demos to talk about
to illustrate uh somebody asked why are
we subtracting 16
that's to put space to get our stack
frame
so this is subtracting 16 from the stack
pointer so it's moving it down basically
in memory
um moving it down so that we now have
space for our own stack frame and then
we can stick stuff there
so because uh at this point in fact we
don't want to override what's at the
stack pointer uh
why not four is just um
well four
we need to do 16 because instructions
are 64.
uh yeah i guess i guess we wouldn't
don't actually need to do 16 but that's
generally what you'll see
um you'll generally just see i don't
think yeah
you you can't you can't do four because
uh you need eight so four doesn't work
but i think you can do
uh you need the instruction size
and the size of the register right so
registers are 64.
yeah and then so the convention why you
usually see 16 is because if we jump
back to our document
usually we have the return address and
the frame pointer
uh but we're not doing that here because
we're being uh
not super careful with our assembly
so normally if we if we look in
i'm sure if we look in kernel.asm we'll
see
yeah so if we look in kernel. we see
it's also you know 16 this is generally
what you'll see with the compiler
um okay so
now we can go back to this
fixed our function and now we can look
at some c
code
all right so here we have demo four
which is just basically um a copy of a
main function
like a imitation of the main function
so we have our args
which is an array of strings and we have
dummy main which takes
uh the number of arguments and the
arguments frame
and just prints it out um for us
and so that's all that's that's all
that's happening here it's pretty
straightforward
uh if we set a breakpoint in
dummy main
and we pop over let this
okay we let this continue and we we
start this
we run down four okay so we now we've
hit
um dummy main and there's a couple of uh
important things to uh remember about
uh that you can use gdp for regarding
stack frames
so if we type i so again that's info
if we type iframe we can see a whole
bunch of uh
useful information about the current
stack frame
so we can see we're at stack level zero
level zero means
it's uh earth is down in the call stack
that we can go
and the frame is at this address
the program counter which is okay that's
all well and good
we have a save program counter as well
and if we
again if we take this address and we
jump
into kernel.asm
[Music]
and we search for that address we can
indeed see
that that address is inside of
inside of demo form which is exactly
where we expect
the program to return to and it was
called by a frame at this address source
language c
you know that's that's nice to know and
then we have the argument list
also starts at this address of course
in this case we have most of our
arguments in
registers uh and then we can even see
what
args are we mean rxc is three
and rv is this address
and if we want to more in depth examine
things we can look at things like
info arcs which will tell us information
about the arguments of the function
we can look at but more importantly
we can type if we type back trace or bt
works as well
we get a full back trace of all of the
stacks uh the all of the stack frames
from the call stack so you can see you
know something questionable happened
here that's when we invoked a system
call um then we get to the user track
function
then to the syscall function then to
sysdemo
then to demo four and then finally to
dummy main
and if we want to investigate any of
these stack frames
more in depth we can do frame and then
whatever number
uh is along the side here so let's say i
want to look at what was my stack frame
when six calls are called i can go to
frame three and so now i'm
inside of gdb i'm looking at that stack
frame so if i type info frame
i can get this and here we get a lot
more
a lot more information we have a bunch
of saved registers
we have some local variables we don't
have any arguments to this function
we can see where the program counter
where we're supposed to jump back to
um all kinds of things like that so this
is super super useful for
if you're debugging things and in fact
it's so useful we make you implement
um your own version not nowhere near and
as
in depth as what udb tells you but we're
one of the exercises on the next lab
will be to implement your own
backtrace helper function for use when
debugging things inside the lab
and so back back traces uh is quite
useful and then if we type frame 0 or we
go back to
where we were supposed to be
and if we want to investigate you
probably noticed it's not super helpful
you know rv is a string
as an array of strings and so we just
get a ref we just get a
an address for where that's actually
stored
and if we want to look at what's in
there there's a couple ways of doing
this
uh the easiest is uh if we type print p
is for print and then if we d
uh dereference the address so we go look
at what's at the
address we can do that and
you know as you would expect we get the
first element of that array because
when it tries to print a string it'll go
you know as c says it'll go in until it
hits the null character
so we get foo which is the first element
that array and if we want to get more
things
we can put in the length so if we do
and then a number it'll go up to a
certain index so then we can see
both of the strings here and
you know again gdb is quite smart so we
can even
use rxe to print out the whole argument
array
and so all of that information is
available to you
however you you want to get it so gdp is
a super powerful tool
why does gdb or sorry why does the
compiler sometimes
optimize out rg c
and rgb that has happened to be before
yeah uh that just means that the
compiler found a more efficient way
likely it just got rid of the variable
and it's doing all of its operations
um directly you know via regis it might
be doing all of its operations on a0 for
example
it might just be doing all of its
computations on the return address
it's pretty common to see something like
that if you um
if it's a variable that's not you know
necessary uh if you you know we don't
let
we don't give you control over the
compiler but if you ever find that in
your day-to-day
you can try setting the optimization
flag for the compiler to zero
um but even then you know the compiler
will do we'll do its we'll do some level
of optimization
uh your hand is raised yeah
um what's the address besides
that dollar one or dollar two you know
like before foo
or bar uh dollar this
yeah so what's that address is that the
address where
foo is probably yeah
but but then rv points to some other
address shouldn't those be the same
uh so our rv is on the stack
and it'll so the reason why
you know if you look at these addresses
we can see that they're in the kernel
uh just by the eight zero zero zero
um which makes sense because we they're
declared statically right so in demos if
i go here they're declared here
and so they're basically they're sitting
somewhere in the kernel and they're all
car stars
args arcs or rv is an array of car stars
and so i imagine that each element
points to points to
its own string right so it's an array of
pointers
crazy
i also have a question about this uh the
dollar three version of
the array has if i look
at these addresses the first one is
suffixed by
38. second one is suffixed by 40.
the third one is 48 which is
not uniform even though the length of
each of the three arguments
is three so why why are they different
uh not in i'm not 100
certain my guess is that this is an
attempt to align things
um right so to get them on a reasonable
alignment and it is uniform in hex as
people are pointing out
oh right yeah yeah that makes sense
oh oh yes i see it now yeah right
thanks so you'll sometimes see where
straight things are
laid out strangely where there might be
two things at strange offsets and that's
just
because not everything is uh naturally
the same size
um okay any other questions
okay uh we can skip the fifth demo
and so another useful function that we
get
from gdb are
instead of just break points uh there
are also watch points and we can also
set
conditional break points so
i'll just briefly go over that
we run demo six so we can set
inside this function we can watch so we
can set a watch point
um i think here you'll see um
yeah so here you'll see what uh luca was
talking about where
we see that sum has been optimized out
likely because it's just being
put in a zero or something we can look
even at the assembly for this right so
we can do layout
splits and yeah indeed we can see that
it all just being uh
it's all just being done on the stack it
looks like to me
oh no it's all just being done in s0
s013
so here you can see that the the
compiler decided even to use the quality
saved registers
and so we can set things like we can do
watch
on i
or we haven't declared i yet because
we're not inside
we're not inside the for loop so if we
step through the c instructions now if
we do information for the locals we see
we get i
we can even watch um watchpoint on
sum so now anytime that sum changes
we'll actually get a notification so we
can continue
and then we'll get a delete here because
some
has been removed so we can't we can't
actually watch it
we can even do things like break points
on sum2 so this is a conditional
breakpoint
if well let's actually see what is i
currently so i is currently one let's
say
i think my loop is breaking and whenever
i is five
well if i want to specifically debug
that case i can set a breakpoint
on sum2
if i equals five
so now we have this breakpoint and if we
continue along
we'll get to some two and uh we can see
that it actually printed out
the first couple values and so we only
break now on some two
if if i if we hit that breakpoint
condition
and so that's uh this can be again this
can be useful if you want to debug
specific edge cases of your code
and watch points can be useful if for
instance you think that something
shouldn't be changing
but you suspect that it is or you think
that something is going wrong
every time you change a certain variable
and so that's that's uh that's one one
usage for that
and uh the last thing i want to talk
about today is structs
structs are pretty important and they'll
come up in
um in the labs often
and also so what asks
i'll talk a little bit about the way
structs are laid out in memory
and so a struct is basically um it's a
continuous contiguous area of memory so
if we have some struct
and we have like field one field two
field three when we make that struck
those fields are going to be
aligned next to each other in memories
and you can kind of think of this
like an array but f1 f2 and f3 can all
be different types
and uh we can uh
pass them as functions usually they're
past uh pass them as arguments to
functions
usually they're passed by reference so
here i've made a struct person
with two integer arguments and
i'm passing them passing a person as an
argument to print person
and uh printing out some of that
information
so if we hop into gdb and let's delete
all of our breakpoints and watch points
and now we can set a breakpoint at
person and let's continue
and run seventh demo
we can see that now we're here and so if
we type iframe
we can see that we have an argument p
and indeed we can if we do print
p if we can even tell that it's a struct
person
at this address and
we can if we dereference it
gdb will tell us exactly what p looks
like it has id 1215
age is 22 and just to show kind of how
things are
laid out we can take this address
and we do x hd at this
i address exactly
so if we again so we can use this to
debug
our structures in
in the code we can take a look at what's
going on
with structures this way so gdb is a
super powerful tool
not just for you know stepping through
code but also for examining
all kinds of potentially problematic
pieces in your code and looking at
arguments and stack frames and things
like that
and this will be hopefully will be
useful in the next lab
when you have to work with um with stack
frames and with assembly code
so that's that's mostly what i wanted to
talk about today so
with the last kind of seven minutes of
lecture
i'll open it up to any any other
questions that you guys have
i had a bit of a tangential question who
is in who manages the the creation of
compilers
from like to get from c to various uh
instruction set architectures is that
the creator of the instruction set
architecture is it a third party
something like that
um i believe that it is
not the creator of the instruction set
so it's often a third party
so the two big c compilers that you'll
see refer to are gcc
which is maintained by i think the gnu
foundation
and uh c lang or llvm
which is its own thing so i think you
know you can find
i believe lovm is even open source so
you can find
um you can you can find the code
specifically that does this
uh when a new instruction set is
released such as risk five
that calling convention document as well
as all of those instruction documents
uh i think you're careful but i assume
there's like a high level of cooperation
between the compiler designer and the
instruction set designer
um but yeah short answer is i i believe
it's a third
third party who does it likely with a
lot of cooperation from the people who
make the instruction set
risk five is probably risk five might be
an exception where because it came out
of a research project
they may have written the the compiler
for it themselves
as well i i don't think intel has
for example has input in uh in gcc or
llvm
other questions
okay well uh thanks
for listening in that case and i guess
嗯
这节课就讲到这里
剩余的五分钟
留给大家好好休息